so hi my name is Joe brewer and I'm a
change strategist I'm working to bring
together different fields of knowledge
and science and design that focus on how
to achieve intentional cultural change
at the societal scale and I in these
videos i offer book reviews on topics
that I think may be helpful for other
culture designers like myself to be able
to engage in these change strategies and
the topic that I want to discuss with
all of you today is the topic of the
political mind now you may or may not be
familiar with the work of George Lake
off he is a linguistics professor at the
University of California in Berkeley and
he's one of the founders of the field of
cognitive linguistics and this book that
I want to review today moral politics
how liberals and conservatives think was
originally published in 1999 this is the
second edition that came out in 2003 so
more than ten years ago almost 15 years
ago and what george lakoff did in his
work is he mapped out the conceptual
structure of the world views and
ideology for liberals and conservatives
in u.s. politics now how did he do this
well you need to know a little bit more
about his background so george lakoff is
a linguist and he was one of the
founders of the field of what's called
embodied cognition which is the way that
we understand how the mind works by
looking at the structures in the brain
in our bodies and persistently
throughout our social experiences as
people with bodies moving around in the
world and now the very structures in our
brains that let us use our bodies are
exactly the same structures that we use
to reason with to feelings about things
and to think about things and so what
George Lake off did in the early 1980s
as a predecessor to this work is he
partnered with a philosopher named Mark
Johnson and they studied what are called
conceptual metaphors oh really briefly
the metaphors that we use to reason
about the world are basically the
process is where we have knowledge from
one domain of our experience and we use
it to guide our thinking about another
domain of our experience and in politics
turns out that there's one very very
important metaphor that george lakoff
discovered in has
work and that metaphor is the nation as
family now this isn't literally saying
that we treat nations as they're as if
there are families it's more accurate to
say that in our early life experiences
we have a number of things that we are
directly exposed to in our family
environments how there are different
kinds of authority different ways of
learning right from wrong different ways
of establishing social norms and
expected behavior and that there are
consistent patterns across these
experiences or growing up in our family
that become foundational inputs for us
to understand politics and how to govern
said another way the first times where
we have consistent experiences of people
making decisions as a group and
understanding how that happens is in our
homes as children with our families or
in common stories about how families
make decisions in popular media within
our culture and what george lakoff found
was that when he looked at this metaphor
that the nation is a family then we'd
start to see a language that makes sense
like we have founding fathers we have
the mothers of the Constitution we send
our sons and daughters off to war that
these phrases only make sense if we are
conceptualizing the nation as if it was
a family and this begs the very
important question what kind of family
is it and what lake off found when he
looked at the language commonly used by
political conservatives and the language
commonly used my political liberals was
that there were two coherent what you
might call dynamic attractors or stable
ways stable configurations for thinking
about worldview and ideology morality
and social behavior and he gave them the
the names of strict father morality and
nurturing parent morality just turned
out to be a little confusing because
people tend to apply gender to it I find
it easier to talk about it as
authoritarian values that are top-down
hierarchies with some moral authority
that's on top that is got submissive
people down below them or subordinate
subordinate people down below them and
that they learn right from wrong through
discipline punishment and reward
contrast this with the other common way
of organizing morality which is based in
empathy compassion
nerds and in this model of morality
people learn white right from wrong from
role modeling basically I will
demonstrate good behavior and you will
learn it through emotional connection to
my behavior in the relationships that I
have with you and that the way we learn
right from wrong is through this kind of
molding of social expectations about how
to treat people how we want to be
treated and it's grounded in a very
fundamental way and the ability to take
perspectives and cultivate empathy so
what he found was that when we apply
these two different ways of
understanding morality to families and
governing decisions they explain a great
deal about politics in the United States
so specifically people who tend to vote
conservative or for Republicans will
often have this authoritarian top-down
discipline-based reward and Punishment
world view whereas people who tend to be
more liberal or progressive will have
more of a nurturer and empathy based
egalitarian worldview what everyone is
worthy of basic rights where we should
care about the suffering that happens to
other people that all people are created
equal and you can see that even in the
founding documents of our Constitution
and our Declaration of Independence
you'll actually find both of these
worldviews and conflict with each other
so the long history of politics in the
United States is an ideological struggle
between different ways of understanding
how we should govern and this book
systematically explores these two
worldviews and how there are many
different variations on how they can
appear to explain the way that
libertarians are different from
evangelical Christians the way that
urban progressives may be different than
say Southern Baptists civil rights
activists and that it maps on two
different social values and social
issues in a variety of ways that are
very systematic and this is important
for anyone that's trying to engage in
political change because if we're unable
to understand how our language is a
mirror or a reflection of the deeper
foundational understandings we have
about morality right and wrong and how
to govern a society then we're going to
be very limited in our ability to
understand how politic
works how it's changing and what we can
do to influence it to achieve goals that
are good for society as a whole using
political pathways so if there is any
work you're doing in the social change
world that involves political thinking
morality social behavior having to do
with group decision-making or formal
political systems elections political
parties etc then this is a foundational
book that I highly recommend and I
really cannot stress enough the
importance of this work for really
grappling with the nuances of the many
different moral worldviews that people
have or I should say the idiosyncratic
expressions of these two systemic
worldviews the egalitarian and the
authoritarian or the authority based
versus the empathy and compassion based
and another point to keep in mind is
that every person has some combination
of both and so the question becomes to
which extent two weeks be speaking to
the authentic values of a person from an
authoritarian point of view or from an
empathy and nurturance point of view and
when we understand those differences we
can engage people in more respectful and
inclusive dialogue and better understand
how to use politics to achieve social
goals so there you go grab your copy
today moral politics by George Lake off
and go and do effective cultural design
work on the topics that you're
passionate about enjoy